Described derisively, the National
Football League acts as a structure
through which young men can sell the
entertainment value derived from the
destruction of their brains. Detractors
and fans would debate that statement
endlessly, but to the league itself,
what's true hardly matters. What matters
is what people believe. One can hardly
overstate just how colossal the NFL is.
Whether by revenue per team, revenue per
game, or just revenue outright, it is by
far the largest sports league in the
[music] world. Its annual revenue is
similar to that of McDonald's. Just one
team, the Dallas Cowboys, is about as
big financially as Planet [music]
Fitness, the largest gym chain in the
world. The only live broadcast to have
ever been viewed by more Americans than
a Super Bowl was the Apollo 11 moon
landing. Well, each week about one in
every 16 Americans tunes [music] in to
their Sunday Night Football broadcast,
making it the most successful TV program
to have ever existed. But this supremacy
is facing a reckoning because more and
more people are coming to believe that
American football is bad. More and more
people are being convinced by the
scientific evidence that American
football frequently causes permanent
damage to the brain, leading to
debilitating cognitive dysfunction later
in life. The immediate risk to the
league's financial [music] interests is
not that people are going to tune out on
mass out of discomfort with the way
their dollars incentivize neural
destruction. Football has always been
perceived as a dangerous sport. It's
something different, but something that
the NFL is taking seriously as one of
the biggest long-term threats to
America's most popular contact sport.
But as a point of comparison, take ice
hockey, America's [music] second most
popular contact sport. While the
National Hockey League has admitted the
danger of brain injuries in its sport
and implemented changes to mitigate
their impact, the league appears far
less concerned than the NFL in the
threat to its financials. But on the
surface level, it looks like they should
be. According to Harvard research into
the matter, the NFL has a per game per
player concussion rate that's 3.8 times
higher than that of the NHL. In a given
game, a professional football player is
far likelier to get a concussion than a
professional hockey player. But what
that actually means in practice is that
in a season, the hockey player is
likelier to get a concussion since the
NHL schedule includes 4.8 times more
games than the NFL. Other studies back
this up. Ice hockey has a similar, if
not slightly higher rate of concussions
than American football. The thing is
though, a single concussion is rarely a
long-term issue. Typically, although not
always, it's a short-term problem
involving short-term cognitive
impairment. A high school athlete might
struggle to retain knowledge for a test.
They might become irritable more often
with their parents. They might be highly
sensitive to light and noise. But
typically, these symptoms subside within
a couple of weeks. A subset of
concussions do lead to long-term or
permanent issues. And the likelihood of
these goes up with each additional
concussion one receives, but permanent
cognitive [music] impairment,
specifically from sports induced
concussions, is rare. And it's even
rarer that these permanent impairments
are [music] significant.
Concussion rates are a misleading
indicator for the volume of cognitive
disability a sport is likely to create.
Ice hockey players frequently skate
faster than 20 m or 32 km/h, which leads
to some very big hits. But compared to
football, these hits happen at a
different rate. Checks are only legal
against a player in possession of a puck
and can only be made from the front or
to the [music] side. Checking from
behind is strictly prohibited, punished
with some of the costliest penalties in
the sport, as it can lead to one's head
or spine absorbing the brunt of the
impact into the boards. Typically,
checking is also focused against the
boards whose glass flexes and absorbs
some of the impact since offense can
more effectively evade defense in center
ice. When put into practice, this means
that hits are relatively infrequent. One
study found that men's college hockey
players experienced an average of 287
head impacts in [music] a season. In
football though, head impacts occur
between 1,00 and 1,500 times a season
and potentially even more with certain
positions. To those that know the game,
this makes sense. The action that most
commonly ends a play is a player on
defense tackling the ball carrier, which
frequently involves a head impact. The
primary way the offensive side stops
that from happening is by physically
blocking opposing players, once again,
frequently involving a head impact. The
data suggests that a given head impact
in football might be less likely than
one in hockey to cause a concussion,
perhaps due to the higher speeds on the
ice. But each one of those more frequent
impacts in football adds to a hefty
accumulated sum of head trauma. And this
cumulative head impact has been found to
be far more correlated with the chances
of future cognitive disability than
simple concussion rates. The subtleties
of that conclusion matter a tremendous
amount to tackle football's future. If
concussions alone were the problem,
there'd be more the sport could do. It'd
be easier to manufacture a rule set that
reduced the likelihood of the high
impact collisions likeliest to lead to a
concussion. And the consequences of
concussions can be genuinely reduced
through proper identification, [music]
treatment, and return to play protocols.
But the growing academic consensus that
total accumulated head trauma is what
matters most suggests that the most
iconic feature of the sport, the contact
is inextricably linked to future
cognitive dysfunction. [music]
The chain of events that dominoed into
that conclusion kicked off here at
Pittsburgh's Alagany County Medical
Examiner's Office in September 2002. The
neuropathologist on call, Dr. Bentomalu
knew little of American football, having
immigrated from Nigeria less than a
decade prior, making him one of the few
people in the office who didn't
recognize the name attached to the
corpse that arrived overnight. [music]
Mike Webster, former Pittsburgh Steelers
legend. Back in the 70s, Webster had
nationwide name recognition thanks to
his central role in the Steelers
fourtime Super Bowlinning offensive
[music] line. In almost every play of
every game of each of his 17 seasons as
a professional football player, he
started by snapping the ball back to the
quarterback, then charging forward and
colliding head-on with the opposing
team's defensive [music] line, adding up
to hit after hit. But game after game,
season after season, no matter how hard
the hit, he'd keep lining up, earning
him the nickname [music] Iron Mike. Once
his career ended, though, so did his
durability. Progressively, cognitive
dysfunction crept in, and eventually,
Webster struggled with basic memory and
decision-making. He went through massive
mood swings. He'd break into wild
outbursts, and as his symptoms got
worse, he withdrew from his family and
began living out of his pickup truck.
He'd stay awake for days at a time as
his brain was stuck in an endless state
of fight or flight. Then, out of
desperation, he'd use a taser to shock
himself, essentially resetting his
nervous system in a way that allowed him
to drift into sleep. As his ability to
function dwindled further, a local
hospital allowed him to sleep in one of
their unused rooms. And it was there
where he died in September 2002 from
cardiac arrest. The following morning,
as Webster's corpse waited for its
autopsy, Dr. Benalu learned his story
through co-workers in the news. But as
the doctor retells it, he was left
unconvinced that Webster just
spontaneously went from two decades of
disciplined professional athlete life to
one of homelessness, drug addiction, and
petty crime. He thought there must have
been a cause. So despite no obvious
signs of brain disease in the initial
autopsy, Amalu brought a brain tissue
sample to the department of neurology at
the University of Pittsburgh where a
deeper examination found abnormal
accumulations of [music] tow proteins.
The same abnormal accumulations found in
patients with Alzheimer's. But Webster
was too young to have Alzheimer's. It's
exceedingly rare for a 50-year-old. And
a deeper look at the tissue showed
distinct pathology. This was something
different, something that had never yet
been found in a football player. This
was chronic traumatic [music]
encphylopathy.
CTE is a hard disease to diagnose.
[music]
While symptoms exhibit in a person's
actions, as of today, the only way to
definitively diagnose it is after death
in an autopsy. The degree of examination
needed is not one included in most
autopsies. So to even have a shot at
diagnosis, brain tissue needs to be
sampled, preserved, and sent to a
specialist within hours of death. Even
then there's a degree of subjectivity to
diagnosis as CTE is identified not based
on the presence or quantity of tow
proteins but [music] rather their
placement and layout in the brain. In
practice that means that the vast
majority of CTE cases go undiagnosed and
therefore researchers have little data
to help to determine the disease's
cause.
While Dr. Omalu and his collaborators
were able to publish a paper about their
diagnosis, the revelation alone had
limited consequences for the NFL. That
was until a few years later when another
Steelers offensive lineman, Terry Long,
died, leading to his body arriving once
again at the Alagany County Medical
Examiner's Office. Dr. Amalu took
another sample for study [music] and
there was evidence of CTE. A pattern was
starting to form and Amalu went on the
offensive, accumulating permission to
examine samples from more and more
former football players. Time and again,
he and his partners diagnosed CTE in
these brains at an extraordinary rate,
and the evidence mounted. With each new
positive specimen, the correlation
between football participation and CTE
was growing irrefutable.
That didn't stop the NFL from refuting
it, though. They rolled out the big
tobacco strategy and started with
denial, hiring their own researchers to
put out their own papers discrediting
the work of Amalu and others. Behind the
scenes, the league orchestrated pressure
campaigns on the academic journals
publishing the CTE research using their
hired academics to sew doubt into
methodologies and conclusions. But
towards the end of the 2000s, Congress
caught on to this and the House
Judiciary Committee summoned NFL
Commissioner Roger Goodell to testify on
the matter, bringing media attention and
public pressure on the matter to its
zenith. Despite the NFL's best efforts,
a wide swath of America now believed the
truth that football caused CTE. And the
pervasiveness of this knowledge is what
convinced the NFL that it could no
longer prevent the crisis. Rather, they
had no choice but to address it. In the
boardroom, however, the crisis was not
exactly one of player health. The
league's executives repeatedly
demonstrated that they considered bodily
damage the cost of doing business for
both them and the players. Rather, the
league recognized that it risked a
disruption in their pipeline. Youth
football is critically important to the
NFL's financial interests. Not only is
it where their future stars are born,
but perhaps more importantly, the 999
out of a thousand players who don't make
it to the NFL are the likeliest future
purchasers of NFL tickets, merch, and
cable [music] packages. High school
sports participation data was beginning
to show a plateau in football
participation starting in 2007 as head
trauma awareness increased and parents
grew more hesitant to get their kids
hooked on a dangerous sport. And in
2011, this plateau [music] turned into
an outright decline. The NFL treats
youth football participation as a
leading indicator, meaning this was
perceived as potentially the start of a
slow decadesl long cycle that threatened
their supremacy over the American
spectator sports industry. Therefore,
the league kicked off a campaign to
mitigate the risks of that happening.
Now, if the American fan base was going
to contract, then one obvious solution
was just to find new fans. The NFL has
long dabbled with international
expansion. They played preseason games
outside the US for decades, and they
even ran a spring development league in
Europe for much of the 90s and 2000s.
While they eventually shuttered this out
of lack of financial success, they
replace it with an annual regular season
fixture in London for the following few
years. [music] Now, this was fairly
unique. A true regular season game
occurring on a different continent from
where sports league was based, but it
proved an instrumental component of
growing the burgeoning UK market.
[music] So, as the concussion crisis
reached its peak, the league doubled
down on this strategy. In 2013, they
expanded from one London game to two,
then the next year to three, and they
even went so far as to contribute to the
construction cost of the new Tottenham
Hotspur Stadium in exchange for the
inclusion of a retractable synthetic
American football pitch for their use.
Today, the league has its biggest
international portfolio ever with seven
regular season games in 2025 across Sa
Paulo, Dublin, London, Berlin, and
Madrid. And of course, the games are
only the tentpoles of a deeper strategy
shift towards the rest of the world,
encompassing broadcast deals,
merchandising expansions, and other
efforts to monetize and grow the
clusters of American football fans
outside of America.
But in addition to finding new blood,
the NFL also tried to stop the bleeding.
To fix the youth football problem, the
NFL's efforts coalesed around one
particular solution, flag football. In
this version of the sport, contact is
prohibited or highly restricted. And
rather than tackling acting as the
inhibitor to the ball carrier's
progress, the defensive side attempts to
pull a flag from a belt. Until the
concussion crisis, flag football was
rarely played at a genuinely competitive
level. It was primarily a PE class
activity, but the NFL has poured
considerable resources into making flag
football a viable alternative for tackle
football. To provide structure, it
started a youth league called NFL Flag,
and that's grown to more than 1,600
teams across America. Some data
indicates that flag football is now
played by more youth in America than
tackle football. Undoubtedly, the low
injury risk and minimal equipment
requirements allow for plenty of casual
participation. And as these kids age,
there are increasing opportunities at
the collegiate level, particularly on
the women's side, where there's never
been a mature tackle football ecosystem.
And the NFL recently announced its
intentions to take it to the next level
by launching its own professional flag
football league for both men and women.
But beyond this, the NFL coordinated a
campaign to include flag football in the
Olympics. As a proof of concept, they
sponsored its inclusion in the World
Games, which is an Olympics-like event
facilitating international competition
for non-Olympic sports. [music] The
league also got their own stars in on
the effort by transforming their pro
ball format into a series of skills
exhibitions, including flag football
matches. And finally, they flexed the
full PR muscle of the league into
getting the message of support for
Olympics flag football out to the
[music] world. Ultimately, it worked.
The International Olympic Committee
approved the bid to add it to the 2028
Summer Games in Los Angeles. Although
this is only a one-off inclusion, it
still lends serious legitimacy to the
idea that flag football is a proper
sport, not just a PE activity. But for
as much as flag football might be a
sport, the NFL still faces the issue
that it's a very [music] different
sport. While the rules are similar to
those of tackle football, the strategy
and incentives are fundamentally
different. [music] It's not like the
difference between no contact and
contact ice hockey. Flag football is a
game of agility and speed. Tackle
football is a game of positioning and
force. [music] Elite flag football
players have the leaner builds of soccer
players rather than the big bulky bodies
synonymous with tackle football players.
So, that's to say, the skills from flag
football are only partially transferable
to tackle football. So, it's far from
guaranteed that people will perceive it
as enough the same sport for it to act
as a true alternative in the shrinking
youth football pipeline. It [music]
might create flag football fans, but
will it create football fans?
Of course, the one solution that's
almost guaranteed to work is actually
reducing football's injury risks.
[music] If the NFL can innovate the
sport in a way that dramatically reduces
CTE and concussion rates, all their
troubles would melt away. For over a
decade now, the league has rolled out a
series of rules that create more nuanced
conditions for what types of contact is
and is not allowed. But the biggest rule
change came in 2024 with the league
completely revamping how kickoffs
worked. Previously, [music] the team
started a possession by lining up on
opposite sides of the field. The kicker
would launch the ball far into the other
side and his team would sprint towards
the receiving team, attempting to block
their progress as soon as possible. This
resulted in massive high-speed
collisions given the speed accumulated
from such a long run towards each other.
While kickoffs represented only 6% of
all plays, they were accountable for 12%
of all concussions. The new system is
called the dynamic kickoff. And while
its rules are more complex, the
consequence is that the majority of
players start just 5 yards apart,
massively reducing the speeds at which
they encounter each other. [music]
According to the league's concussion
data, this correlated with a 43%
reduction in concussions during
kickoffs, contributing to a 17%
reduction in concussions overall during
the 2024 season. This change certainly
had its detractors, including American
President Donald Trump. And it certainly
was a highly visible change to one of
football's most iconic plays, [music]
but when the sport has a fundamental
issue, fundamental change is perhaps the
only real fix. Today, [music] two
decades on from the first paper linking
CTE to football, one decade on from a
Golden Globe nominated Hollywood movie
depicting the saga, and mere months on
from a mass shooting in New York
perpetrated by a former football player
with CTE targeting NFL headquarters.
Understanding and awareness of CT's
prevalence and severity is only
progressing further. On the academic
side, in 2018, Boston University did a
study on 164 brains from the general
population and found no evidence of CTE
in 163 of them. The one with CTE was
from a college football player. Among
the 376 brains they've studied from NFL
players, 345 were diagnosed with CTE, a
91.7%
prevalence rate, albeit amongst a biased
sample. [music] A growing number of
states have seriously considered a ban
on tackle football for young kids. And
while proposed legislation has always
been stunted by strong push back, the
trend line suggests it could only be a
matter of time until some states
consider it so dangerous to play tackle
football that it should be treated like
alcohol or tobacco. But despite more
people understanding the degree of
danger of football than ever, all signs
suggest that the NFL has successfully
navigated the threat to its financial
interests, at least for now. After more
than a decade of decline, the emergence
from CO coincided with a reversal in
trend in youth football participation.
It's still nowhere near its peak, but
the bleeding has stopped. [music]
Meanwhile, league revenue is growing as
fast as ever, having cleanly doubled
over the past decade, and the 2025 Super
Bowl was the most watched in history
with 128 million Americans tuning in.
But even if the recent moment was not
the reckoning that the NFL's executives
so feared, [music] and even as the
league is making genuine progress at
reducing the frequency of high impact
collisions, there are still more subtle
trend lines that are pointing the league
towards a form that a future world might
not accept. [music]
Since the revelations into CTE, the
socioeconomic background of youth tackle
football players has tilted downward.
More and more, it's a sport played by
those from poorer families. Meanwhile,
the background of NFL consumers is
growing wealthier. It's [music]
successfully catering to a richer
demographic. Combining a better
understanding of the debilitating health
consequences, [music] talent coming from
poorer backgrounds, and fans coming from
richer backgrounds, the comparisons
between football players and Roman
gladiators are becoming increasingly
literal. For many, football is not
purely a pursuit of passion, but rather
their most realistic chance at escaping
the generational cycles of poverty.
Nobody's forced to play professional
football, but when lacking good
alternatives, their circumstances can be
coercive. Getting to an elite level in
any sport requires a tremendous degree
of sacrifice. Isolation from normal
life, physical and emotional pain,
dedication to a career path that could
end with a single injury. But the
distinction with football and contact
sports like it is near inescapable
damage to the most critical, most
irreplaceable organ in the body. The NFL
brings some of the most life-changing
wealth one can earn in professional
sports, but it involves some of the most
life-changing consequences. So, even if
inertia has won out for now, the
question for the NFL's future is how
much longer people will be comfortable
with what they watch on their couch
dictating how many young men get
condemned to a life of psychological
torment once they hang up the cleats.
If you're trying to decide what to watch
next, well, then I have a suggestion for
you. It's our brand new docky series
called Scav. Basically, myself and the
Wendover team heard about the world's
largest annual scavenger hunt, which
takes place at the University of
Chicago. So, we hired some film crews,
flew to Chicago, spent a week filming
the chaos, and the next couple months
editing to bring you Scav. The first few
episodes are up right now on Nebula, and
this is just one part of the large and
growing catalog of Nebula original
content. We've also made The Getaway, a
social deduction game show on wheels
with a twist, Abolish Everything, a
comedy debate show filmed in front of a
live audience, and the logistics of X, a
Wendover style series explaining some of
the most interesting logistical systems.
And that's just what we've made. There's
a curated collection of 250 or so
creators also posting on Nebula, many of
whom have made their own originals.
Bobby Broccoli, for example, made a
fantastic documentary about one of the
largest scientific controversies of the
20th century, while Real Life Lore has a
series called Mad Kings about the
world's most influential dictators and
kings. I couldn't possibly list off
every original, but if you're the kind
of person who watches a lot of online
video, it's worth giving Nebula a try.
That's because it's creator run and
creator owned, designed to be the best
home for our work. Making it paywalled
instead of ad supported removes the
incentives to chase clicks over quality
and also provides the funding to make
these higher budget, higher caliber
Nebula originals. And of course, even
besides the originals, you still get a
ton of value since we all publish our
regular videos there first and without
any ads or sponsorships. Tens of
thousands of Wendover viewers have
signed up for Nebula. And if you want to
see why, you can do so with a free trial
when you head over to
nebula.tv/wendover.
That link will also get you 40% off an
annual subscription or the lifetime
subscription where you pay once and get
Nebula access forever. Signing up also
helps support us and hundreds of other
independent creators. So, thanks in
advance if you do.